foreign
Trail Recon Adventure my son and I meet
up with some great folks driving some of
the best built off-road vehicles out
there and head to the mountains of
Arizona to tackle the infamous back way
to Crown King Trail and many other
incredible Trails over the next several
days we get after it on some very
technical sections that were not without
a few challenges we take in the amazing
scenery stop at a few local historic
sites and camp at some Deep Off the Grid
amazing locations we enjoy some great
camaraderie of course we eat some
delicious chow and ultimately have an
adventure that we'll never forget
foreign
[Music]
Trail Recon I'm Brad and I am here in
Phoenix Arizona with my son and we are
on day seven of a long adventure that
we've been doing but we've arrived here
for the center Force Adventure 2021 run
where we're gonna go hit some Trails
here in Arizona that I haven't done
before so I'm super excited about that
we've got 13 other cool vehicles that
are going to be hitting the trail we're
gonna be doing some camping we've been
doing some Wheeling we're gonna be
eating some good Chow at Camp so this is
going to be a great adventure I'm super
super excited that you guys are joining
us we're going to do a quick drivers
meeting here and we're gonna be hitting
the dirt here soon this is gonna be
awesome uh Trent is going to be our
Trail Boss uh and he's going to be uh
saying what we can and can't do Center
Force has assembled a great group of
folks and vehicles for this run and
after spending a little time getting the
details at the driver's meeting about
what lay ahead and ensure everybody had
plenty of water food and fuel for the
first leg of this adventure we're off
our trip kicked off with a total group
of 14 very capable rigs here in Peoria
Arizona and over the next three days
we'll be making our way North over 160
miles through some easy and very
challenging Trails we'll be traveling
from the low desert covered in saguaro
cactus to the high mountains in the
thick Pine Forest
after traveling a few miles on the
pavement we made our way to the dirt and
we traveled a few miles on some Scenic
nice easy dirt roads saw some Burrows
along the way and just enjoyed the
scenery and eventually we pulled into a
staging area to air down our tires this
trip we would definitely need to be
aired down to get that extra traction
all right we have just turned off of
Lake Pleasant and we're up here at the
staging area and airing down and then
we're going to be heading up to Crown
King now Crown King is supposed to be a
really fun trail one that I had planned
to do about two years ago we had to
reschedule and so I've been wanting to
come out here for a long time but this
is gonna be cool this is a beautiful
Scenic area we're going to be climbing
up the mountains now one thing that you
might be asking yourself is this is a
center Force run and yes it is they make
clutches and so every vehicle except one
has a manual transmission and that would
be mine so my goal during this uh whole
Adventure is to ask everybody why do
they love Emmanuel so much who knows
maybe they'll convince me to convert
foreign
[Music]
the back way to Crown King is a Jeep
badge of honor Trail I have been wanting
to explore for a couple years and just
haven't made the time to come up here so
I'm pretty excited about today's trail
run this Trail is 34 miles long it's
rated as difficult and while there are a
couple bypasses along the way many of
the obstacles you have to tackle and
they require high clearance and
excellent Tire placement
this Trail is a straight through run and
if traveling from south to North like we
did it takes approximately eight hours
to reach the town of Crown King which
you will see is totally worth it okay
we've got a whole lot of miles ahead of
us and plenty of obstacles to put these
vehicles through today is going to be an
awesome trip on the trail before our
first stop
all right
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
you know manual versus an automatic I
could actually go either way but I
started with the manual I actually
technically prefer one you just have
more control overall it's more difficult
to master especially for off-road use
but once you have it mastered you can
control exactly what gear you're in you
can have the exact gearing you need for
the scenario that's in front of you it's
just a better overall Driving Experience
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
I mentioned that my son and I have been
on a multi-day adventure I'm just having
a blast up to this point this is our
last big adventure together before he
deploys for the next seven months and so
I let him have most of the fun behind
the wheel and while he has plenty of
Driving Experience off-road this was the
first time he has pulled a trailer
through some technical obstacles he made
it look easy over the next three days
now we had been on the trail for a few
hours and had been climbing higher and
higher in elevation with each passing
Mile and the trails seemed to get a
little more challenging around every
corner because the higher we went a
little harder the next obstacle was and
look while I enjoy a nice easy Scenic
Trail it's technical Trails like this
that really get me excited there is
something rewarding about building your
vehicle and then getting out here and
putting it through its paces there are
no Mall crawlers in this crew and this
next little section would be the
toughest of the day
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
when you are navigating through fun
challenging terrain like this having a
good spotter is invaluable but even the
best driver and spotters know their
limits and have to make the call to
preserve the vehicle so grabbing that
winch line is sometimes the best option
we Mount winches on our rigs so we can
safely move along the trail for a reason
no need to break anything especially
this early on in our trip
foreign
[Music]
everyone to the top of the climb it was
time for a quick lunch but nothing fancy
here because we needed to keep moving to
make it to Crown King and Camp before
dark tonight
however one small challenge Sean noticed
a broken valve stem on one of his rear
tires so everyone came together and got
it swapped out in short order
so I was going to use his extension to
pop off the center cap but I can use the
extension on mine
okay we're a good ways into Crown King
and what an awesome Trail and what a
beautiful day with some great people now
we've gone up some really cool obstacles
and of course we pulled some winch and
uh we had a tire valve bust out so we've
replaced that everybody's having some
good lunch and then we're gonna keep on
trucking I know there's still some more
good obstacles and we should have a good
campsite tonight so pretty cool so far
we are moving door
Airport
[Music]
thank you
uh hmm I guess I like driving a manual
because
I feel like you're more in control of
the vehicle uh my mom insisted that I
knew how to drive a manual she was big
into driving manual transmissions and
she taught me how to double clutch and
all that
and uh yeah just
just wouldn't do it any other way
[Music]
so a manual transmission is fun plain
and simple I think that is the one thing
that keeps me coming back to wanting to
continue this uh but then it's the
connectivity to just the machine itself
uh it's definitely a challenge when
you're out on trail but I think being
able to feel each gear and being in
control of what you want the vehicle to
do uh there's something that that's a
quality you just don't get with other
vehicles so
I don't know makes a big difference
[Music]
thank you
as we were slow rolling on this Rocky
section of the trail one of the guys
behind me called out on the radio and
said he thinks I'm leaking some fluid
and a quick inspection revealed that yep
sure enough a few of my differential
bolts had worked their way out enough
and I was losing diff fluid
an easy enough fix and then thankfully
we caught it before the diff Elite
completely dry a good reminder to always
give your rig a once over especially on
long trips like this
[Music]
foreign
all right so the main reason I like to
drive a manual off-road is I feel a lot
more connected to the vehicle when I'm
in the automatic Jeeps it sort of takes
some of the fun out of it it does a lot
of decisions for you but with this guy
with a six-speed manual and you know
really nice clutch setup it's pretty
easy to do things with the jeep that you
can't do with the manual as far as you
know increasing the RPM to go over a
safe obstacle and stuff like that so a
lot more control with the manual
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
as we were climbing higher into the
mountains the green vegetation began to
surround us I think too often folks
assume Arizona is just a Barren desert
but there really is so much more to see
here than just desert one more solid
obstacle lay ahead and then we'll be
arriving to the old mining town of Crown
King which is located in a thick pine
tree Forest
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
s it wasn't long before we arrived to
the small mining town of Crown King
gold was discovered here back in 1875
and the mines were active up until the
1940s
at the height of the gold boom here
there were 500 buildings but today it's
twiddled down to just a few most notably
is the General Store the fire station
and of course the saloon survived
we took a nice break while we were in
town soaked in the atmosphere and we
were told to be sure to try the fudge at
the General Store you don't have to tell
me twice about fudge
after getting our fill we made our way
to camp for the night
well the Crown King Trail was awesome
and day one of the center Force
Adventure has been amazing we've had a
great time you know we've gone through
some struggles but we've all come out on
the end we made it to Camp it's got
everybody's getting all set up dinner is
going to be going here soon it's going
to be a great night now it is we're up
in the mountains we're about 6 700 feet
so it's getting a little chilly so
Jordan's already got his jacket on I
think I'm gonna throw mine on here soon
but I know Ali is going to be cooking
dinner so I'm excited to see what he is
cooking up and then we'll be hanging
around the campfire just to join
everybody's company but this is just day
one of three we still got two more days
of some cool trail riding to go
this camping spot was perfect a nice big
flat area to accommodate all of us with
our diverse camping Styles there's no
right or wrong way to Camp whether it's
a rooftop tent or a ground tent or even
just sleeping on the ground there's
plenty of choices that can accommodate
everyone's personal preference
as folks we're getting all set up Ollie
was ramping up the kitchen
oh hey brother uh before we talk about
what you're cooking for dinner tonight
because I know you've graciously
volunteered to cook dinner what'd you
think about the trail today Trail is
really great
um one of our guys over at KC Taylor had
done this Trail in advance and he kind
of rubbed it in our faces with his
videos and so the saloon like at the end
ending on the saloon probably one of the
coolest things and the trail itself had
a lot of challenging parts and just a
lot of nice beautiful scenic areas cool
awesome well I've enjoyed it today now
what are you cooking up for dinner
tonight so I'm Do What I Call Persian
burritos it's basically Persian chicken
kebab beef kebab and then we throw that
into some lavash bread with a little bit
of uh shallot yogurt and some sliced
cucumbers it's delicious everyone seems
to like it so hopefully today we'll get
uh some more fans awesome buddy well I
can't wait to dive in thanks man
it's no easy feat to cook dinner at camp
for this bigger group and Ali had lots
of marinated chicken on hand that he
skewered and grilled over the Open Flame
yeah you could see how much work he was
putting in and the joy it was bringing
him to cook for everyone
the chicken was cooked to Perfection
with the bread and all the fixings it
was delicious and not a single person
was left wanting more
we had had an amazing day on the trail
and now with full bellies it was time to
hang out around the campfire reminisce
about the day's events and what was to
come tomorrow
[Music]
oh
foreign
[Music]
thank you
well good morning what a beautiful
morning it is waking up to the fresh air
the pine trees the birds chirping and it
was a great night last night we were
afraid it was going to be a little too
chilly but it was actually pretty warm
in the tent and this morning having some
coffee eating a little breakfast just
hanging out with everybody it's just
been a nice relaxing morning now we're
packing up and getting ready to hit the
trail and I honestly have no idea where
we're going today but it should be fun
and we'll end up at another cool
campsite hopefully like this tonight
eating some good chow and just having
some good camaraderie today's gonna be a
fun day I'm excited to see what's to
come
after a nice relaxing morning and just
before the driver's meeting we needed to
recognize a young man who in my opinion
was spending a birthday the best way you
can on an adventure happy birthday
to you
so did we uh we have a good day
yesterday it was fantastic yeah so it
was a lot of technical stuff you know
you could kind of make it as hard or as
easy as you wanted to so it was a good
day we didn't uh well I guess we broke
some stuff but not a whole lot of stuff
which is good let's hope that that Trend
continues today so what we're going to
do is uh we're gonna get out of here
we're gonna head back towards Crown King
we're actually gonna go blow by it we're
gonna go by the cleaner yacht club which
will become important later
um and we're gonna go do a trail called
Turkey Creek
um it is aptly named because there's a
creek down there and we're gonna cross
it about 20 or 30 times but it's a real
cool Trail it's probably there's there's
a couple of spots on it but it's not as
maybe as hard as what yesterday was so
uh very Scenic at the beginning the ends
of it's a little bit bumpy but at the
end of it is something kind of cool that
we're gonna check out as well
everybody's just about packed up so if
anything we might actually get out of
here maybe a little bit early this is
going to be a long day so I'm I'm
probably gonna pushing a little bit
harder to
to keep everybody rolling because we do
have a lot of miles to cover this way so
uh so anyway we're gonna oh and then
after uh we get done with Ricky Creek
we're gonna kind of backtrack a bit into
Spring Valley and get some fuel so we'll
we'll top off and then we're gonna go do
a portion of the Great Western Trail
right on well yeah let's finish getting
packed up and we'll get out of here in
just a few minutes
the driver's meeting all wrapped up all
the vehicles packed up and back on the
trail it was time to begin our descent
down at the other side of the mountain
to begin the next leg of this trip over
the next two days we'll put in just over
a hundred miles on the dirt and explore
some Unforgettable places
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
it wasn't long until we reached the
bottom of the mountain and turned off of
Crown King Road onto Turkey Creek
Turkey Creek is an 11 Mile Trail that
zigzags through the mountains in a
northwesterly direction crossing the
creek several times this Trail is
difficult and there are some sections
that require high clearance and a couple
of tight technical areas that will
demand some excellent driving skills
what kind of Trail we like all right
let's go get after it
[Applause]
[Music]
thank you
all right
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
basically would turn from a liquid
liquid hot magma into a solid rocks
usually Underground
so that among the crackers rock that has
uh was either at a monster truck which
is sort of confusing igneous rock or
sedimentary rock but then got heated up
or pressurized enough to almost liquefy
it but not quite
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
we had been on the trail for a few hours
and everybody was having a blast thus
far and up to this point all the
obstacles were navigated pretty easily
but this section did get a little
off-camber while making a sharp turn now
it doesn't look so intense on camera but
let me tell you the seat of the pants
feeling here will make you definitely
slow down
Vern's Jeep made easy work of this but
Marco and I with the trailers did have
to slow down and take things easy but
they didn't stop us from being able to
navigate this just fine I think what was
most interesting was the XJ
this is the least built vehicle of the
group but lease built doesn't equal
least capable this old XJ was climbing
over everything this whole trip with
ease just goes to show you that you
don't need to spend a lot of money to
have a great adventure okay let's hear
from Sean as to why he loves driving a
manual on the trail
so my preference for manual comes from
uh obviously way better control way
better crawl ratio I feel like today
everybody's gone to like 40 inch tires
automatic and so much of what we love
and what we grew up doing off-roading
was all about your lines and pick you
know really technical sections and kind
of picking your way through obstacles
and today I feel like it's so point and
shoot you know you just go that way hit
the throttle and you don't have to do
anything but steer and it's sort of
boring so being on the trail with a
manual and being able to operate three
pedals and a shifter and a steering
wheel and actually use your brain to get
around all my friends who wield oh dude
you you automatically they laugh at me
for being the manual guy so this thing
with 488 gears 37s manual trans is 101
to one crawl ratio I mean how do you
beat that
everything is
[Music]
foreign
this next obstacle for the Dale on the
trail is one that is a little technical
because you are hugging a rock wall on
the driver's side and there is a good
drop off on the passenger side and it's
a bit rutted out with some loose rocks
you really need to take your time here
going too fast could cause your
suspension to bounce a bit and if you
didn't get the line right you could go
too close to the edge and then well it
could be a bad rollover situation having
a second set of eyes was just a little
bit extra peace of mind as we all inched
our way through this but no problems
well at the age of 10 my parents taught
me how to drive a manual just in case my
mom had to give birth and I had to drive
her to the hospital so ever since then
I've driven a stick shift and honestly
it makes me feel really connected to the
vehicle in ways that an automatic just
doesn't do it
the remainder of Turkey Creek is not
terribly technical but bumpy enough to
keep your speed down and we were running
a little behind schedule for our planned
lunch stop
[Music]
foreign
also be lunch
we're a little bit behind schedule so
let's try to make it as quick as
possible
we arrived to the old gold mining town
of cleator a little later than expected
but this is a must stop location if
you're in the area cleaner is an old
gold mining town that was established in
1864 and is a popular destination for
off-roaders exploring in this area the
town is filled with lots of eclectic
items and the most popular stop here is
yes a yacht club in the middle of the
desert be sure to go into the bar and
say hello and check out all the
memorabilia and grab a cold one while
you're here
during our lunch stop the guys from
Summit a local off-road shop made an
on-trail house call to come out and fix
one of American Adventure Labs Jeep
brake lines talk about service these
guys were awesome
we've had a great day today out on the
trail coming down from the mountains and
into the desert and running Turkey Creek
and now we've ended up here and there's
a yacht club here we're in the middle of
the desert and yes there is a big yacht
behind me a little out of place but kind
of eclectic it's kind of cool now we are
having some lunch getting a couple
little repairs done and then we are
gonna head down the Great Western Trail
we got a lot more miles to put in find a
good camping spot but it's been a great
day
awesome time
after leaving our Mark in the bars
registry book it was time to head out of
town we did stop to top off our fuel
tanks as many of the non-diesel vehicles
were getting pretty low on fuel but we
still had many miles to go so everybody
needed to top off here
the next leg of our adventure will take
us along the bloody Basin Trail and then
on to a section of the Great Western
Trail the Great Western Trail is a 4
455 Mile Trail system that goes from
Canada all the way down to Mexico but
unfortunately not all of the trail is
motorized and a good portion of it is
hiking only but there's still hundreds
of miles to explore in a vehicle
this was the easiest section of terrain
on this trip so far and it was kind of
nice to take a little bit of a driving
break and sit back and just Cruise along
and enjoy the scenic dirt road our
camping spot is just up ahead
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
all right so we're wrapping up day two
and it has been a great day but we have
put in a lot of miles going through
Turkey Creek and then coming through the
Great Western Trail it's been awesome we
finally found a really nice Camp spot
out here in the woods along this River
it's a little tight but we're gonna make
it fit and Marco has got dinner duty
tonight so I know dinner's gonna be good
it's gonna be a good night and the
temperature is pretty good so we should
be set tonight you guys are skipping
rocks behind us this is going to be
great fun
[Applause]
your best
buddy what is going on man what a day it
was awesome this Trail is amazing yeah I
mean it was just it was a little long
but it was fun it was fun I don't think
we've ever camped here in a spot like
this it's a little tight in here but
it's kind of cool it's kind of Riverview
you're cooking right on the water I
don't know river is a little bit of a
stretch okay I know you're excited about
what you're making for dinner tonight
I've had this before but tell everybody
what you're making tonight making birria
okay what is that on the on the pressure
cooker so it's I made this adobo with
different Chiles and the meat has been
marinating in that adobo there's
actually the recipes on my channel yeah
buddy remember yep yeah dead guys
definitely go check out Overland X on
YouTube uh lots of great cooking videos
over there and Marco I know the Camp's
gonna be smelling good here soon and I
also like that we brought an off-road
apple pie yep you guys come in here
because Marco volunteered to cook dinner
for such a large group tonight he had
prepared many of tonight's meal in
advance but of course he insisted the
salsa had to be made fresh
Marco you've got a new blender dude that
used to be a little tiny handle blender
what's going on with this big one well
the little one I have to make the
sauces in batches yeah this just make
the whole salsa once
nice well you've got a big battery pack
so no problem running that no problem
right 1500 watts all right man smelling
good dude
foreign
as Marco was working on dinner preps
everybody else was getting settled in
the sun did begin to set and the
temperature started to drop it's going
to be a little chilly tonight
I took a few moments tonight to walk
around camp and check out how everyone
was packing up their vehicles I always
find it interesting to see what people
bring with them on long trips like this
and how they decide to pack them
some are more organized and others are a
little more casual there's really no
right or a wrong way here just whatever
works for you but it's always cool to
look
dinner as always when Marco was cooking
was delicious
Spirits were high around camp and we had
a great evening around the fire what an
amazing day
around here
[Music]
foreign
everybody it is a beautiful morning out
here got the sun coming up on the trees
got the creek here we've got the smell
of breakfast and laughter in the
background it has just been a perfect
morning we're no rush today we're just
gonna kind of get up casually go and
then we've got more of the Great Western
Trail that we're going to explore today
this is our last day on the trail but
I'll tell you what we've been having a
lot of fun this group uh this has been a
fun group to hang out with so today's
gonna be good fun guys I can't wait to
get started
foreign
[Music]
I just wanted to say thanks to our camp
chefs throughout the weekend Ollie Marco
and then Jeff this morning with some
awesome pancakes
super super awesome Yep
[Applause]
to serve that level of Cuisine out here
in the middle of nowhere so yeah the
next level truly so yeah
um so today is going to be a lot like
yesterday afternoon just very very
beautiful but bumpy and slow
but nothing super hard or anything like
that so the master plan is we are just
right outside at the thriving Metropolis
of Dugas which is a consists of about
six or seven shacks and maybe a house
we're gonna cross back over the 17 so
we'll be over on the west side of it
again uh we'll be on Highway 169 which
is actually kind of a back way to
Prescott as you call it that
um but we're only going to be on the
road for like a mile since we're not
going to worry about airing up or
anything like that we're going to turn
off and we're going to continue on the
Great Western Trail but we're going to
be going through cherry and eventually
making our way up back into the pine
trees uh we'll kind of be skirting
around the back side of Mount Mingus
which is outside of Cottonwood for those
of you that familiar with that
um and then we will be popping out on
89A
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
well we've been on the trail for a while
today we put in a lot of miles and we've
arrived up here in the mountains in the
pine trees to stop for lunch and that's
what I love about Arizona is you know
you think of Arizona as this hot Barren
desert but you can be up in the
mountains we're over 6 700 feet in the
pine trees it's beautiful up here this
is awesome this entire trip has been
amazing a huge thanks to Center Force
for inviting us out here and a special
thanks to Trent for leading us through
all these amazing trails and seeing all
these great places this has been such a
wonderful Adventure I hope you guys have
enjoyed checking it out if you're not a
subscriber hit that subscribe button
because you don't want to miss our next
adventure thanks for watching